<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<databasecriterion>
    <criterion>
        <name>Cleanliness of water points</name>
        <description>Check the level of cleanliness of the waters points.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Check the level of cleanliness of the waters points.<br><br>All water points in question are assessed within the area of the animal unit where behavioural observations have been made.<br>Check the cleanliness of the water points with regard to presence of old or fresh dirt on the inner side of the bowl or trough as well as staining of the water.<br> Water points are considered as clean when there is no evidence of crusts of dirt (e.g. faeces, mould) and/or decayed food residues. Note that some amount of fresh food is acceptable.<br>]]></help>
        <category>Alimentación</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Water provision</name>
        <description>Check the type and number of water points.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Check the type and number of water points.<br><br>All water points in question are assessed within the area of the animal unit where behavioural observations have been made.<br>Check for the type of the water points. In the case of open and tip-over troughs, measure the length of the trough.<br>In case of bowls with reservoirs, bowls, nipple drinkers or drinkers with balls/antifrost devices, count the number of water points.<br>If a water point from an adjacent pen is accessible, count it as ‘half’(both for number and length in case of a trough).]]></help>
        <category>Alimentación</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Body condition score</name>
        <description>View the body</description>
        <help><![CDATA[View the animal from behind and from the side in the loin, tail head and vertebrae. Animals must not be touched but only watched.<br>Animals are scored with regard to four criteria as follows<br><table border="1"><tr><td><b>Body region</b></td><td><b>Very lean</b></td></tr><tr><td>Tail head</td><td>Cavity around tail head</td></tr><tr><td>Loin</td><td>Visible depresssion between backbone and hip bones (tuber coxae)</td></tr><tr><td>Vertebrae</td><td>Ends of transverse processes distinguishable</td></tr><tr><td>General</td><td>Tail head, hip bones (tuber coxae), spine and ribs visible</td></tr></table>]]></help>
        <category>Alimentación</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Number of animals using the water points</name>
        <description>Number of animals in the pen having access to the water points</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Number of animals in the pen having access to the water points.<br><br>All water points in question are assessed within the area of the animal unit where behavioural measures have been made. <br>Count the number of animals per pen that have access to the water points.]]></help>
        <category>Alimentación</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Time needed to lie down</name>
        <description>Check the time that the animal is lying down and the all observable “lying down” movements.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Check the time that the animal is lying down and the all observable “lying down” movements.<br><br>This measure applies to fattening cattle of more than 350 kg live weight, description and applies to all observable ‘lying down’ movements (minimum sample size of 8 is required). <br><br>Time needed to lie down is recorded continuously according to the following method: time recording of a lying down sequence starts when one carpal joint of the animal is bent and lowered (before touching the ground). The whole lying down movement ends when the hind quarter of the animal has fallen down (touched the ground) and the animal has pulled the front leg out from underneath the body.<br><br>Record the time needed to lie down. Observations take place in pens or, in the case of very large pen sizes, in segments of pens. Per segment not more than 25 animals should be assessed on average. Total net (overall) observation time is a maximum of 120 minutes depending on the weight class distribution in the farm together with social behaviour).<br><br>﻿Minimum duration of observation per pen/segment is 10 minutes.]]></help>
        <category>Refugio</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Cleanliness of the animals</name>
        <description>Observe the level of cleanliness of the body including the underbelly.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe the level of cleanliness of the body including the underbelly.<br><br>From a distance not exceeding 2 m, one side of the focal animal is examined including as much of the underbelly as is visible but excluding head, neck and legs below the carpal joint and hock (tarsal joint), respectively.<br>The criterion for cleanliness is the degree of dirt on the body parts considered :<br><br>- covering with liquid dirt<br><br>-plaques: three-dimensional layers of dirt<br><br>Random selection of the side of the animal observed (left or right) has to be ensured. To prevent biased results, the side selection has to be done before the examination. In most cases, the side which is seen first when approaching the animal can be chosen.]]></help>
        <category>Refugio</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Pen features according to live weight</name>
        <description>Check the length and width of the pens</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Check the length and width of the pens and calculate  the number of animals and estimated weight of the animals in kg (per 100 kg)<br><br>The length and width of the pens is measured. The number of animals in each pen is counted. The average weight of the fattening cattle is estimated in each pen in categories of 100 kg (e.g. 200, 300, 400… kg).]]></help>
        <category>Refugio</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Access to outdoor loafing area or pasture</name>
        <description>Check the availability of an outdoor loafing area and/or access to pasture and the respective conditions.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Check the availability of an outdoor loafing area and/or access to pasture and the respective conditions.<br> The animal unit manager is asked about pasture management (days per year, average time spent in outdoor loafing area/pasture per day).]]></help>
        <category>Refugio</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Lameness</name>
        <description>Observe the lameness of the animals and its degree.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe the lameness of the animals and its degree.<br>Lameness describes an abnormality of movement and is most evident when the animal (and so the legs) is in motion. It is caused by reduced ability to use one or more limbs in a normal manner.<br><br>Lameness can vary in severity from reduced mobility to inability to bear weight. Assess the animal for presence of one of the indicators mentioned below, according  to  the  description  for  either  standing  or  moving animals.<br><br>Indicators in moving animals:<ul><li>Reluctance to bear weight on a foot</li><li>Uneven temporal rhythm between hoof beats, weight not borne for equal time on each of the four feet.</li></ul>Indicators in standing animals:<ul><li>Resting a foot (bearing less/no weight on one foot).</li><li>Frequent weight shifting between feet (“stepping”), or repeated ovements of the same foot</li><li>Standing on the edge of a step</li></ul>]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Hair</name>
        <description>Observe the hair of the animals.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe el pelo del animal y evalue según la longitud del pelo, su asentamiento y el brillo]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Salud de la ubre</name>
        <description>Con los análisis, compruebe la salud de la ubre</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Pida al ganadero los análisis o realice los análisis y evalúe según el recuento de las células somáticas, la bacteriología y la mamitis sufridas en la última lactación.]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Integument alterations</name>
        <description>Observe the hairless patches and lesions/swellings and their extension on the body of the animal</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe the hairless patches and lesions/swellings and their extension on the body of the animal.<br>Integument alternations are defined as hairless patches and lesions/swellings. Assess one side of the animal for integument alterations.<br><br>Hairless patches and lesions/swellings are counted in accordance with the criteria provided below: Only skin alterations of a minimum diameter of 2 cm at the largest extent are counted.<br>Hairless patch<br><ul><li>area with hair loss</li><li>skin not damaged</li><li>extensive thinning of the coat due to parasites</li><li>hyperkeratosis possible</li></ul>Lesion/swelling<br><ul><li>damaged skin either in form of a scab or a wound</li><li>dermatitis due to ectoparasites</li><li>ear lesions due to torn off ear tags</li></ul>From a distance not exceeding 2 m, three body regions on one side of the assessed animal have to be examined with regard to the criteria listed above.<br><br>﻿These body regions are scanned from the rear to the front, excluding the bottom side of the belly and the inner side of the legs, but including the inner side of the opposite hind leg.<br>Random side selection (left or right) has to be ensured. To prevent biased results, the side selection has to be done before the examination. In most cases, the side which is seen first when approaching the animal can be chosen. <br>If there are different categories of alterations at the same location (e.g. swelling and lesion at one leg joint) or adjacent to each other (e.g. a round hairless patch with a lesion in its centre) all these alterations are counted.]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Coughing</name>
        <description>Count the number of coughs per animal. The animals must not be touched.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Count the number of coughs per animal. The animals must not be touched.<br><br>Coughing is defined as a sudden and noisy expulsion of air from the lungs.<br><br>The number of coughs is counted using continuous observations in pens or, in the case of very large pen sizes, in segments of the pens. Per segment not more than 25 animals should be assessed on average.<br><br>Total net observation time is 120 minutes. Recording of coughs is carried  out  together  with  social  behaviour  and  resting  behaviour observations]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Nasal discharge</name>
        <description>Observe the nasal discharge (Color and consistency). The animals must not be touched.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe the nasal discharge (Color and consistency). The animals must not be touched.<br><br>Nasal discharge is defined as clearly visible flow/discharge from the nostrils; it can be transparent to yellow/green and often is of thick consistency.<br>
            <br>﻿The animal is observed but must not be touched. Animals are scored with regard to the nasal discharge criteria.]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Ocular discharge</name>
        <description>Observe the level of teardrops of the animal. The animals must not be touched.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe the level of teardrops of the animal. The animals must not be touched.<br><br>Ocular discharge is defined as clearly visible flow/discharge (wet or dry) from the eye, at least 3 cm long.<br><br>The animal is observed but must not be touched. Animals are scored with regard to the ocular discharge criteria.]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Hampered respiration</name>
        <description>Observe the animal and count the hampered respiration rate. The animals must not be touched.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe the animal and count the hampered respiration rate. The animals must not be touched.<br><br>Hampered respiration rate is defined as deep and overtly difficult or laboured breathing. Expiration is visibly supported by the muscles of the trunk, often accompanied by a pronounced sound. <br><br>Breathing rate may only be slightly increased. The animal is observed but must not be touched. Animals are scored with regard to the criteria for hampered respiration.]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Diarrhoea</name>
        <description>Observe the animal and calculate the affected area by the illness. The animal must not be touched.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe the animal and calculate the affected area by the illness. The animal must not be touched.<br><br>Diarrhoea is defined as loose watery manure below the tail head on both sides of the tail, with the area affected at least the size of a hand.<br><br>
            The animal is observed but must not be touched. Animals are scored with regard to the criteria of diarrhoea.]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Bloated rumen</name>
        <description>Observe the rumen of the animal and classify it according to the diferent types of rumen.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe the rumen of the animal and classify it according to the diferent types of rumen.<br><br>Bloated rumen is defined as a characteristic “bulge” between the hip bone and the ribs on the left side of the animal.<br>The animal is observed but must not be touched. Animals are scored with regard to the criteria of bloated rumen.]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Mortality</name>
        <description>Rate the mortality of the farm. Check the farm records.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Rate the mortality of the farm. Check the farm records.<br><br>
            Mortality is defined as the ‘uncontrolled’ death of animals as well as cases of euthanasia and emergency slaughter.<br><br>The animal unit manager is asked about the number of animals which died on the farm, were euthanized due to disease or accidents, or were emergency slaughtered during the last 12 months. <br><br>Additionally theaverage number of animals with a weight of more than 200 kg live weight in the animal unit is asked. Farm records may also be used.]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Disbudding/dehorning</name>
        <description>Check the disbudding or dehorning of the animals.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Check the disbudding or dehorning of the animals.<br><br>The animal unit manager is asked about the disbudding/dehorning practices on the farm with regard to the following:<ul><li>Procedures for disbudding calves or dehorning fattening cattle</li><li>Use of anaesthetics</li><li>Use of analgesics</li></ul>]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Castration</name>
        <description>Check the use of castration methods on the farm.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Check the use of castration methods on the farm.<br>The animal unit manager is asked about castration practices on the farm with regard to the following:<ul><li>Procedures for castration</li><li>Use of anaesthetics</li><li>Use of analgesics</li></ul>]]></help>
        <category>Salud</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Agonistic behaviours</name>
        <description>Observe the agonistic behaviour of the animals.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe the behaviour of the animals. Agonistic behaviour is defined as social behaviour related to social hierarchy and includes aggressive as well as submissive behaviours.<br><br>Agonistic behaviour is defined as social behaviour related to social hierarchy and includes aggressive as well as submissive behaviours.<br><br>Here, only aggressive interactions are taken into account. Assess the occurrence of the behaviours listed below. Observations take place in pens or segments of pens. On farms with more than 12 pens in question (live weight >200 kg), the maximum number of 12 pens is observed for 10 min net observation time each.<br><br>Pens with more than 25 animals are divided into 2 or more segments, which will also be observed for 10 min per segment and this thus reduces the total number of pens observed. Pens containing animals with a weight between 200 and 350 kg and animals with more than 350 kg live weight are observed proportionally to their presence within the ﻿observation  time.  Pens  observed  should always  be  approximately randomly distributed across the barn(s) and also within the weight categories.<br><br>Total net (overall) observation time is 120 minutes. Minimum duration of observation per segment is 10 minutes. Agonistic behaviours are recorded using continuous behaviour sampling always taking the animal carrying out the action (actor) into account. Interactions between animals in different segments are recorded if the head of the animal carrying out the action (actor) is located in the focus segment.<br><br><table border="1"><tr><td>Parameter</td><td>Description</td></tr><tr><td>Head butt</td><td>Interaction involving physical contact where the actor is butting, hitting, thrusting, striking or pushing the receiver with forehead, horns or horn base with a forceful movement; the receiver does not give up its present position.</td></tr><tr><td>Displacement</td><td>Interaction involving physical contact where the actor is butting, hitting, thrusting, striking, pushing or penetrating the receiver with forehead, horns, horn base or any other part of the body with a forceful movement and as a result the receiver gives up its position (walking away  for at  least  half  an  animal-length  or stepping aside for at least one animal-width).<br>Penetrating is defined as an animal forcing itself between two other animals or between an animal and barn equipment (e.g. at feeding rack, at water trough). If after a displacement neighbouring animals also leave their feeding places but physical contact as described above is not involved, this reaction is not recorded as displacement.</td></tr><tr><td>Chasing </td><td> The actor makes an animal flee by following fast or running  behind  it,  sometimes  also  using threats like jerky head movements. Chasing is only recorded if it follows an interaction with physical contact. If, however, chasing occurs in the context of fighting then it is not counted separately.</td></tr><tr><td>Fighting</td><td><ul><li>Two contestants vigorously pushing their heads (foreheads, horn bases and/or horns) against each  other  while  planting  their  feet on the ground in sawbuck position and both exerting force against each other. </li><li>Pushing movements from the side are not recorded as head butt as long as they are part of the fighting sequence. </li><li>A new bout starts if the same animals restart fighting after more than 10 seconds or if the fighting partner changes.</li></td></tr><tr><td>Chasing-up</td><td>The actor uses forceful physical contact (e.g. butting, pushing, and shoving) against a lying animal which makes the receiver rise.</td></tr></table>Before  starting  and  after  finishing  the  behaviour  observation in  a pen/segment the number of animals present in the pen/segment has to ﻿be counted. In the case of multiple segments within a pen, animals which are found lying, standing or feeding across the boundaries of segments are counted in the section where the main part of their body is situated.<br><br>Note that agonistic and cohesive behaviours are recorded at the same time and therefore the number of animals at the start and the end of each observation period is only recorded once.]]></help>
        <category>Comportamiento</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Cohesive behaviours</name>
        <description>Observe the cohesive behaviour of the animals.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe the behaviour of the animals. Cohesive behaviour is defined as behaviour promoting group cohesion. Assess the occurrence of the behaviours listed below.<br><br>Cohesive behaviour is defined as behaviour promoting group cohesion. Assess the occurrence of the behaviours listed below.<br><br>Observations take place in pens or segments of pens. On farms with more than 12 pens in question (in weight >200 kg), the maximum number of 12 pens is observed for 10 min net observation time each. Pens with more than 25 animals are divided into 2 or more segments, which will also be observed for 10 min per segment and thus this reduce the total number of pens observed. Pens containing animals with a weight between 200-350 kg and animals with more than 350 kg live weight are observed proportionally to their presence. Pens observed should always be approximately randomly distributed across the barn(s) and also within the weight categories.<br><br>Total net (overall) observation time is 120 minutes. Minimum duration of observation per pen/segment is 10 minutes.<br><br>Cohesive behaviours are recorded using continuous behaviour sampling always taking the actor into account. Interactions between animals in different segments are recorded if the actor’s head is located in the focus segment.<br><br>Before starting and after finishing the behaviour observation in a pen/segment the number of animals present in the pen/segment has to be counted. In the case of multiple segments within a pen, animals which are found lying, standing or feeding across the boundaries of segments are counted in the section where the main part of their body is situated.<br><br><table border="1"><tr><td>Parameter</td><td>Description</td></tr><tr><td>Social Licking</td><td>The actor touches with its tongue any part of the body (head, neck, torso, legs, and tail) of another group mate except for the  anal region or the prepuce. If the actor stops licking for more than 10 s and then starts licking the same receiver again, this is recorded as a new bout. It is also taken as a new bout, if the actor starts licking another receiver or if there is a role reversal between actor and receiver.</td></tr><tr><td>Horning</td><td>Head play with physical contact of two animals: The animals rub foreheads, horn bases or horns against the head or neck of one another without obvious agonistic intention. Neither of the opponents takes advantage of the situation in order to become a victor. It is taken as a new bout if the same animals start horning after 10 seconds or more or if the horning partner changes.</td></tr></table><br><br>Note that agonistic and cohesive behaviours are recorded at the same time and therefore the number of animals at the start and the end of each observation period is only recorded once.]]></help>
        <category>Comportamiento</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Access to pasture</name>
        <description>Access to pasture</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Check the availability of access to pasture. If pasture is available, the animal unit manager is asked about pasture management (days per year, average time spent on pasture per day).]]></help>
        <category>Comportamiento</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Avoidance distance</name>
        <description>Observe and check the distance to the animal before the animal refuses human contact.</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Observe and check the distance to the animal before the animal refuses human contact.<br><br>Test at least half of the animals in a pen. In the case of hard sizes ≥100, where sample size is less than 50% of the animals, randomly select the number of pens necessary to reach the sample size; however proportions of weight classes should still be considered; the pens selected for the behavioural observations should be included.<br><br>Place yourself on the feed bunk at a distance of 3 meters (if possible) in front of the animal to be tested. The head of the animal has to be completely past the feeding rack / neck rail over the feed. If you do not have 3 meters in front of the animals in which to approach them, then choose an angle of up to 45 degrees with the feeding rack, and start at a distance of 3.5 meters. If a distance of 3.5 meters is not possible, continue with the assessment but note down the maximum distance possible on the recording sheet.<br><br>Make sure that the animal is attentive or is taking notice of your presence. If an animal is not obviously attentive, but also not clearly distracted, it can be tested. A way to attract the animals’ attention is to make some movements in front of them (at the starting position).<br><br>﻿Approach the animal at a speed of one step per second and a step length of approximately 60 cm with the arm held overhand at an angle of approximately 45°  from the body. When approaching, always direct the back of the hand toward the animal. Do not look into the animal’s eyes but look at the muzzle. Continue to walk towards the animal until signs of withdrawal occur, or until you can touch the nose/muzzle.<br><br>Withdrawal movement is defined as the following behaviours: the animal moves back, turns the head to the side, or pulls back the head trying to get out of the feeding rack; head shaking can also be found.<br><br>In the case of withdrawal the avoidance distance is estimated (=distance between the hand and the muzzle at the moment of withdrawal) with a resolution of 10 cm (300 cm to 10 cm possible). If withdrawal takes place at a distance lower than 10 cm, the test result is still 10 cm. If you can touch the nose/muzzle, an avoidance distance of zero cm is recorded.<br><br>Make sure that the hand is always closest to the animal during the approach (not the knee or the feet). Especially when getting close to animals that are feeding or have their heads in a low position, bend a little in order to try to touch them.<br><br>Note that neighbouring animals react to an animal being tested and so should be tested later on. In order to reduce the risk of influencing the neighbour’s test result, every second animal can be chosen. Retest animals at a later time if the reaction was unclear.]]></help>
        <category>Comportamiento</category>
    </criterion>
    
    <criterion>
        <name>Qualitative behaviour assessment</name>
        <description>Considers  the  expressive quality of how animals behave and interact with each other and their environment</description>
        <help><![CDATA[Considers  the  expressive quality of how animals behave and interact with each other and their environment.<br><br>Qualitative  Behaviour  Assessment (QBA)  considers  the  expressive quality of how animals behave and interact with each other and the environment, i.e. their ‘body language’.<br><br>Select between one and eight observation points (depending on the size and structure of the farm) that together cover the different areas of the farm. Decide the order to visit these observation points, wait a few minutes to allow the animals to return to undisturbed behaviour. Watch the animals that can be seen well from that point and observe the expressive quality of their activity at group level. It is likely that the animals will initially be disturbed, but their response to this can be included in the assessment. Total observation time should not exceed 20 minutes, and so the time taken at each observation point depends on the number of points selected for a farm:<br><br>﻿When observation at all selected points has been completed, find a quiet spot and score the 20 descriptors.Please note that scoring is not done during observation, and that only one integrative assessment is made per farm.<br><br>The terms used for QBA in fattening cattle are:<ul><li>Active</li><li>Relaxed</li><li>Uncomfortable</li><li>Calm</li><li>Content</li><li>Tense</li><li>Enjoying</li><li>Indifferent</li><li>Frustrated</li><li>Friendly</li><li>Bored</li><li>Positively occupied</li><li>Inquisitive</li><li>Irritable</li><li>Nervous</li><li>Boisterous</li><li>Sociable</li><li>Uneasy</li><li>Happy</li><li>Distressed</li></ul>]]></help>
        <category>Comportamiento</category>
    </criterion>
</databasecriterion>
